Guide to the Anne X. Alpern Papers, 1918-1974 AIS.2002.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Anne X. Alpern Papers
1918-1974
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Alpern, Anne X.
AIS.2002.01
17.6 Linear Feet (30 boxes)
Anne X. Alpern was a renowned jurist hailing from Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. She served as city solicitor of Pittsburgh during the 1940s and in 1959 became attorney general of Pennsylvania, the first woman to hold such an office in the United States. Alpern's papers highlight her activities and career achievements and provide a glimpse of her family life and hobbies. Court case files and newspaper clippings represent the bulk of the collection, but there are also other materials such as letters and photographs.
Biography
Anne X. Alpern was a renowned jurist hailing from Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. She served as city solicitor of Pittsburgh during the 1940s and in 1959 became attorney general of Pennsylvania, the first woman to hold such an office in the United States. Born in Russia in 1903, she moved to the United States shortly thereafter with her family, settling in Scenery Hill near Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. Although Alpern was interested in law from an early age, she trained as a teacher, receiving a Bachelor's Degree in education from the University of Pittsburgh in 1923. Encouraged by her father, Joseph Alpern, she received her law degree from the University of Pittsburgh in 1927. Soon after she began working for the local law firm of Cunningham Galbraith & Dickson. At the time, female attorneys were not generally given the chance to argue court cases, but Alpern was persistent in her request for such an opportunity. Her employers gave her a case that nobody else wanted, and after a single night's preparation, Alpern went to court the next day and won. Within days she used this intense preparation method again, in another successful case. She continued this practice throughout her career.
In 1934, city solicitor Ward Bonsall hired Alpern to assist with a large backlog after Mayor McNair's election. Alpern worked long hours, though the job was temporary and without pay, often staying in her office all night. Her hard work led to success in cases such as Westinghouse Air Brake Co. v. City of Pittsburgh, which saved the city millions of dollars. As a result of her success, Bonsall promoted her to first assistant city solicitor in 1935. She quickly gained a reputation for a dramatic flair in the courtroom as well as an impressive mastery of the law. In 1942, Alpern was appointed city solicitor by Mayor Scully, the first time in Pittsburgh's history that a woman had been appointed to this position. In 1946, she was admitted as an attorney of the U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit. That same year she worked with Mayor Lawrence to obtain a temporary injunction against a strike by workers for Duquesne Light which caused a brief blackout in the city. This was the first of several actions which exemplified her impartiality in the eyes of many, even as it alienated some of her supporters in organized labor and the Democratic Party. As city solicitor, Alpern was noted for promoting smoke control and improvements of the public transit system, resisting increases in utility rates and trolley fares, and working to expose and remove government corruption. She was a member of the National Institute of Municipal Law Officers (NIMLO), serving as president from 1947 to 1948, and worked with the Public Parking Authority of the City of Pittsburgh from 1947 to 1951.
In November 1953 Anne Alpern ended her service as city solicitor when she was elected judge of the Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County. Although the Democratic Party had nominated her, Alpern was elected with strong bi-partisan support. In 1959, the recently elected Governor Lawrence appointed Alpern to the position of attorney general for the state of Pennsylvania. This was the first time in United States history that a woman held such a position in state government. Alpern's jurisdiction in this office included the state police and the Department of Justice. One of her major projects as county judge and as attorney general was the reduction of case backlogs in Pennsylvania's courts – she frequently said that "justice delayed is justice denied". Alpern helped put regulations in place to prevent the abuse of money donated to public charities. She also worked unsuccessfully for the creation of a state-level Division of Consumer Protection, arguing that the Public Utility Commission was not effective in protecting people from the depredations of utility companies. In 1960 she began an investigation into allegations of voting fraud in Philadelphia involving the Democratic Party.
Early in 1961, Alpern was offered a position as the head of the Federal Power Commission by John F. Kennedy, but turned it down. In August of the same year, before her term as attorney general was completed, Governor Lawrence appointed Alpern as a justice of the Pennsylvania Supreme Court to fill a sudden vacancy. As an interim appointment to the court, she was required to run in the election of 1961 for a full twenty-one-year term of service. On November 7th she was narrowly defeated by Henry X. O'Brien. Analysts attributed this partly to the support she lost from Democrats after the voting fraud investigation, as well as her work to reduce retail milk prices and her opposition to the 1946 utility strike, which turned some union leaders against her. She also had experienced opposition due to her efforts to reform the state judicial system: her bill authorizing the appointment of court administrators had been defeated by the state legislature in June 1961. To compensate for this defeat, Governor Lawrence named Alpern to the position O'Brien had vacated in the Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County.
In 1962 the University of Pittsburgh conferred an honorary degree of Doctor of Laws on Anne Alpern. During her second term as judge in the county court, she heard the case that resulted in the Port Authority of Allegheny County abandoning its "Skybus" public transit project in 1973. In 1974 Anne Alpern retired from the court and joined the firm of Berkman Ruslander Pohl Lieber & Engel. She died in Pittsburgh in 1981.
Anne Alpern was renowned for her legal achievements and for her success in balancing a public career with a private family life. She married fellow assistant city solicitor Irwin Swiss in 1937 and the couple raised a daughter, Marsha Swiss. Alpern took part in community activities and public charities, serving on the board of the United Jewish Federation, the United Fund, and Action Housing, among others. She received many awards throughout her career, including recognition as a Distinguished Daughter of Pennsylvania in 1952, the Newspaper Guild Award and the Junior Chamber of Commerce Award in 1953, and the Award for Distinguished Public Service from NIMLO in 1953 and 1961. Since 1994, the Pennsylvania Bar Association has bestowed the Anne X. Alpern Award on outstanding female jurists in recognition of excellence and positive impact on women in the legal profession.
Scope and Content Notes
Alpern's papers highlight her activities and career achievements and provide a glimpse of her family life and hobbies. Court case files, some of which are closed, show many of Alpern's cases, both as an attorney and as a judge. Other types of records range from correspondence to reports from professional conferences to photographs. Some of the most readily-usable information is provided by a series of newspaper clippings, in folders and scrapbooks. These cover Alpern's career through articles and political cartoons.
Two sub-series of this collection within Alpern's personal papers come from Alpern's husband Irwin Swiss. These include a very limited set of records from his law practice and public offices, as well as journals, newspaper and magazine clippings, and notes on literature and politics, many pertaining to Zionism.
Further notes are found at the series level.
Arrangement
The contents of the collection are organized into six series:
Series I. Case Files
Series II. Professional Records
Series III. Personal Papers
Series IV. Newspaper Clippings and Scrapbooks
Series V. Photographs
Series VI. Closed Cases
Access Restrictions
This collection contains materials protected by the attorney-client privilege and, therefore, may be subject to review prior to researcher use. In particular, material in Series VI. is closed until further notice in order to ensure compliance with attorney-client privilege laws. Closed files are marked in the contents list. Please contact the Archives Service Center for more information.
Acquisition Information
Gift of University of Pittsburgh Barco Law Library on January 15, 2002.
Custodial History
These papers were housed in the University of Pittsburgh Barco Law Library where they underwent preliminary processing in 1985. They were transferred from the law library to the Archives Service Center in 2002.
Previous Citation
Anne X. Alpern Papers, 1918-1974, AIS.2002.01, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Papers of David Leo Lawrence, 1959-1966, AIS.1978.15, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Records of the Pittsburgh Railways Company, 1872-1974, AIS.1974.29, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Microfilmed Records of the United Jewish Federation of Pittsburgh, 1912-1964, AIS.1997.24, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Genevieve Blatt Papers, 1934-1977, Manuscript Group 283, Pennsylvania State Archives, Harrisburg, Pa. Blatt, a younger contemporary of Alpern and fellow University of Pittsburgh graduate, was the first woman elected to a statewide office in Pennsylvania.
Papers of Juanita Kidd Stout, 1873-1998, MSS84478, Manuscript Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. Stout was another contemporary of Alpern and was the first African-American woman to serve as judge of a court of record or general jurisdiction in the United States. Her papers contain correspondence with Alpern, as well as with Blatt.
Separated Material
Oversized materials and photographs are housed apart from the rest of the collection.
Bound reports and other publications taken from the collection have been cataloged separately. These include two issues of the Jewish Criterion containing articles by Irwin Swiss: "Thoughts and Impressions of the Zionist Convention" (July 6, 1928) and "Palestine in the Contemporary Jewish World" (January 25, 1935). These newspapers can be found in ais Journals.
Bibliography
Garraty, John A. and Mark C. Carnes, eds. "Alpern, Anne X.," American National Biography, Vol. 1. New York: Oxford University Press, 1999: 377-378.
Rubin, Victor. "Portia from Pittsburgh." Collier's October 20, 1946: 44-50.
Burgess, Milton V. "The Alpern Story." Pittsburgh Sun-Telegraph January 28, 1951: 3.
Law -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Law -- Pennsylvania; Women judges -- Pennsylvania; Judges -- Pennsylvania; Women lawyers -- Pennsylvania; Lawyers -- Pennsylvania; Women; Politics; Jurists; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Pennsylvania; Zionism -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Jews -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Local transit -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Alpern, Anne X.; Alpern, Joseph; Pennsylvania. Supreme Court; National Institute of Municipal Law Officers (U.S.); Pennsylvania. Office of the Attorney General; Pittsburgh (Pa.). Department of Law; Public Parking Authority of Pittsburgh (Pa.); Swiss, Irwin A.; Swiss, Marsha; Pennsylvania. Court of Common Pleas (Allegheny County)
- Case Files, 1928-1972 (Bulk 1929-1951); I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  These files represent many of Alpern's cases, either as an attorney or as a judge. In some cases her role is not clearly given by the records present. Most files hold court records and briefs, both typed and printed. A small number of files contain correspondence or newspaper clippings. Files are ordered alphabetically by the surname of the first party named in each case.
  Some files come from Alpern's private practice with Cunningham Galbraith & Dickson and deal with divorce and estates. However, most of these are closed until further notice to ensure compliance with attorney-client privilege laws. Many cases that Alpern argued as city solicitor involved local industry, particularly railroads and utilities. Some significant files from this era include: a writ of prohibition against an investigation that threatened the office of Mayor McNair in 1936 (Box 6, Folder 11); the "Free Work" probes into allegedly illegal use of city labor and materials in 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 5; Box 6, Folder 8); and the "Mesta Machine" case of 1943 (Box 9, Folder 11-14) wherein Alpern defended the taxation by the city of property belonging to the Mesta Machine Company.
  In cases involving the city of Pittsburgh, Alpern represented the city. For other cases, unless noted otherwise, the first name in the case title is the party Alpern represented. In cases where she represented the second party named, the client is identified as appellant or appellee, or as "client" in parentheses. A file at the end of the series contains records from cases sparsely documented or of minor significance, arranged chronologically within the file.
  - Berman, et al v. Duggan, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 723, January Term, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bove, et al v. Pittsburgh Railways Company, Pennsylvania Public Utility Commission, C. 15317, 15327, 15371, 15376, 15407, c1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brinton v. Kerr, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 223 March Term, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Burkman, v. Anderson and the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad Company, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 3994 April Term, 1934; Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 271 March Term, 1936, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 04-05)
  - Carson v Board of Assessors of the City of Pittsburgh, et al, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 866 January Term, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cinker v. Borough of Crafton, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 1523 January Term, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - City of Pittsburgh v. Duquesne Light Company, Pennsylvania Public Utility Commission, Complaint Docket No. 14157-1946, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - City of Pittsburgh v. Kaufmann et al, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 66 October Term, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - City of Pittsburgh, et al v. Waverly Oil Works Company, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - City of Pittsburgh v. Pittsburgh and West Virginia Gas Company and Kentucky West Virginia Gas Company, Docket No. G-627, In the Matter of Pittsburgh and West Virginia Gas Company and Kentucky West Virginia Gas Company, Docket No. G-635, United States Federal Power Commission, Opinion No. 168, March 1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cold Metal Process Company v. United Engineering & Foundry Company, United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit, No. 6700, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Commonwealth v. Hoak, et al (before Judge Strauss), Court of Common Pleas of Dauphin County (Criminal Division), OT Nos. 112, 113, 114, 115, 117, 516 April Sessions, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Commonwealth v. Kirk, et al, Court of Oyer and Terminer and General Jail Delivery and Quarter Sessions of the Peace of Dauphin County, No. 303, 304, 305 January Sessions, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 01-05)
  - Commonwealth v. Lawrence, et al, Court of Oyer and Terminer and General Jail Delivery and Quarter Sessions of the Peace of Dauphin County, September Sessions, 1938, No. 301, January Sessions, 1939, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Commonwealth v. Saunders, Appellant, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 145 March Term, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Commonwealth ex rel. City of Pittsburgh v. Heiman, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Sitting at Pittsburgh, No. 98 April Term, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Commonwealth ex. rel. Flowers v. Flowers, Appeal of the Equitable Building and Loan Association, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 172 March Term, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Commonwealth ex. rel. Park v. Kaiserman (client), Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 3509 January Term, 1938; Commonwealth ex. rel. Park v. DiCenzo, et al, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 3929 January Term (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Commonwealth ex rel. Schofield v. Lindsay, Appellee, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 166 March Term, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Conley v. Firemen's Relief and Pension Fund Board of the City of Pittsburgh, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Sitting at Pittsburgh, No. 158 April Term, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - In re: Application of DeBolt Transfer, Pennsylvania Public Utility Commission, Application Docket No. A. 29719 - Folder No. 5, c1937 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Dornan v. Philadelphia Housing Authority, et al, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Eastern District, No. 235 January Term, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Duquesne Light Co. Financial Information, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - F.J. Kress Box Company, et al v. City of Pittsburgh, et al, Supreme Court of the United States, No. 954 October Term, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Finley v. McNair, Appellant, and Moritz, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 233 March Term, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Finley v. Pension Board of the City of Pittsburgh, Appellants, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 85 April Term, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Flaherty, et al v. Port Authority of Allegheny County, et al ("Skybus"), Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 313 April Term, 1972; No. 41 March Term, 1973, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
  - General Motors Acceptance Corporation v. Baltimore and Ohio Railroad Company, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Returnable at Pittsburgh, No. 89 April Term, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Glesenkamp v. City of Pittsburgh, et al, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 191 March Term, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - In re: Grand Jury Investigation of violations of the law in the use of city labor & materials of the city of Pgh. ("Free Work" Probe #1), Court of Oyer and Terminer and General Jail Delivery and Quarter Sessions of the Peace of Allegheny County, No. 59, September Sessions, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Green v. City of Pittsburgh, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 22 March Term, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Gretton v. City of Pittsburgh, et al, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Sitting at Pittsburgh, No. 113 April Term, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Higbee Estate, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, Nos. 61, 62 March Term, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Howe Divorce, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Jackson Estate, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Jacob v. City of Pittsburgh, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 98 March Term, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - John Benkart & Sons Company v. Pennsylvania Public Utility Commission (DeBolt Transfer, Intervening Appellees), Superior Court of Pennsylvania, Pittsburgh District, No. 172 April Term, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Kurtz v. City of Pittsburgh, et al, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 1259 Miscellaneous Docket (Original Jurisdiction), undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Lloyd v. City of Pittsburgh, et al, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 1603 October Term, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Mannella v. City of Pittsburgh, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Sitting at Pittsburgh, No. 80 March Term, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
  - In Re. McCarter ("Free Work" Scandal #2), 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - McCarthy v. City of Pittsburgh and Musgrave, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Sitting at Pittsburgh, Nos. 201, 202, 203, 204 April Term, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - In Re. Petition of McNair for Writ of Prohibition, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 876 Miscellaneous Docket of 1936 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - McSorley v. Public Parking Authority of Pittsburgh and City of Pittsburgh, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 115 March Term, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - In re: Right of Metropolitan Utilities District, Omaha, Nebraska, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Miller v. Seaman, et al (clients), Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 218 April Term, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Nash Divorce, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - National Biscuit Co. Appeal to Re-trial of O'Donnell v. Kroger, c1934 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Orth v. Doench, et al, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 125 March Term, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - In re: Petitions of Patterson and Marshall, in re: Municipal Election of November 2, 1937 (Democratic judges, clients), Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 2289 January Term, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Pellegrini, v. Radiant Society, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 999 October Term, 1940, 1940-1943 (Box 5, Folder 06-07)
  - Pennsylvania Power & Light Company v. City of Bethlehem, et al, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Eastern District, No. 247 January Term, 1936; No. 28 January Term, 1937, 1936-1937 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Pennsylvania Railroad Company v. City of Pittsburgh, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 81 March Term, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - In re: Appeal of Perrin from the Decision of the Board of Adjustment, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, Nos. 78 and 100 March Term, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - In re: Insurance Trust of Petty, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 39 March Term, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Pittsburgh Paving Company, for Use of Iron & Glass Dollar Savings Bank of Birmingham v. City of Pittsburgh, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 184 March Term, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - In re: Pittsburgh Railways Company, Debtor, United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit, Nos. 8964, 8967, 8996 October Term, 1945; United States District Court for the Western District of Pennsylvania, No. 20225 In Bankruptcy, 1945-1950 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Pittsburgh Terminal Warehouse & Transfer Company v. City of Pittsburgh, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 19 March Term, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Roberts v. Pitt Publishing Company, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 202 March Term, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Scholnick, Inc. v. Blanck, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 3059 October Term, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Scholnick Inc. v. Temple Restaurant, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 1310 July Term, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - In re: Appeal of Skarvelis from the Decision of the Board of Adjustment, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 133 March Term, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - State of New York, et al v. United States of America (City of New York and National Institute of Municipal Law Officers, Amici Curiae), Supreme Court of the United States, No. 5 October Term, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Steinberg v. United States of America, United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit, No. 11,793, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Stevens v. City of Pittsburgh, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 89 March Term, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Taskey v. City of Pittsburgh, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 245 April Term, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - United States of America and Mesta Machine Co. v. Allegheny County, Supreme Court of the United States, No. 417 October Term, 1943, 1943-1944 (Box 6, Folder 10-13)
  - Voltz v. General Motors Acceptance Corp., Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 151 March Term, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 1)